Clare Talbot Papers
© 2002 University of Connecticut
Clare Talbot Papers.
1751-1985.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Talbot, Clare.
2.6 linear feet.
The collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, papers, articles, reviews, notes, publications, background materials, photographs, photocopies, photostats, negatives, and order forms related to Calre Talbot's writings, as well as her business activities.
MSS19980224
Biography
Clare Ryan Talbot was born on August 9, 1899 in Charles City, Ohio to Thomas Joseph and Margaret Ann (Darby) Ryan. She attended St. Mary's Academy and College from 1914 to 1918 and the University of Oregon from 1919 to 1920. She married E.C. Talbot on October 1, 1931, but they later divorced. In 1945, she married the antiques dealer W.R. Bill, who died in 1952.
Clare was an avid bookplate collector and most of her professional and non-professional activities revolved around this interest. She was a collector, appraiser, dealer, writer, and historian of bookplates. Throughout her life, she operated various shops, including Clare's Collector's Books, Wind River Bill Antiques, and Clare's Curiosity Shop: "Antiques and Books About Them", in which she sold bookplates, rare and specialty books, and antiques. She was also the director of the Hilprand Press, which was established in order to publish works about bookplates and bibliographies of bookplate literature.
She wrote a number of different articles and also wrote and delivered several lectures regarding the subject of bookplates. She was the books editor of Western Collector magazine, book reviews editor for Silver Magazine, and contributed regularly to Antiques Journal and several other periodicals. Aside from these shorter pieces, she wrote two published books: In Quest of the Perfect Bookplate (1933) and Historic California in Bookplates (1936; republished 1983). She also wrote several manuscripts for books that were never published, including "Six Centuries of the Bookplate", "Pacific Bookplates", and "Bookplates of the Signers of the Declaration of Independence".
Clare was a founding member of the Society of Ex-Libris Historians, and was a member of a number of different societies about bookplates and other related subjects, including the Bookplate Association International, California Bookplate Society, The American Society of Bookplate Collectors and Designers, and the American Society of Heraldry. In recognition of her various achievements and contributions to bookplate literature and collecting, she was included in the Who's Who in the West, Who's Who of American Women (3rd edition, 1964-1965), World Who's Who of Women (4th edition, 1978), and the International Blue Book (Who's Who in the World, 1943). Clare Talbot died on October 5, 1981 and was survived by her brother Laurence J. Ryan.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, papers, articles, reviews, notes, publications, background materials, photos, photocopies, photostats, negatives, and order forms related to Clare Talbot's writings as well as her business activities (her shop and Hilprand Press). A substantial proportion of the collection is comprised of materials relating to Clare Talbot's work on The Bookplates of the Signers of the Declaration of Independence.
Related Material
Isidore Mendle Collection on the History of Printing located at Washington University [Mo.]. Contact curator for more information regarding bookplates. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Arrangement
The collection was arranged, when possible, according to the original order in which the material was received.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Talbot, Clare Ryan.
Subjects:
Hilprand Press.; Bookplates--Collectors and collecting.; Publishers and publishing--United States.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Photocopies.; Notes.; Photographs.; Negatives.; Fliers (printed matter).
Detailed Description
- Clare Talbot's Writings1751-1985
  - Descriptions of some of Clare's works,undated, 1978 (Box 1:1)
  - Articles and papers,undated, 1938-1965 (Box 1:2)
  - Lecture notes,undated (Box 1:3)
  - In Quest of the Perfect Bookplate: The Whenceabouts of the Collection of Clare Ryan Talbot, 1933
    - Manuscript,1933 (Box 1:4)
    - Notes,undated (Box 1:5)
    - Background materials,undated (Box 1:6)
    - Reviews,undated, 1933 (Box 1:7)
  - Historic California in Bookplates, 1936
    - Notes, background materials,undated, 1924-1979 (Box 1:8)
    - Correspondence,Aug 1933-Jul 1936 (Box 1:9)
    - Reviews, articles,undated, 1935-1985 (Box 1:10)
  - Six Centuries of the Bookplate
    - Manuscript,1940-1967 (Box 1:11)
    - Correspondence,Apr 12, 1941 (Box 1:12)
    - Announcements about book,undated, 1940-[1951?] (Box 1:13)
  - The World of the First Medical Bookplate 1509 and the World it Lived in
    - Announcement, Title Page, Table of Contents,[1966?]-1974 (Box 1:14)
    - Background materials,undated, 1870-1962 (Box 1:15)
    - Medical Translations (Correspondence and Pamphlets),1960-1961 (Box 1:16)
  - The Bookplates of the Signers of the Declaration of Independence
    - Outline of book and of materials for book,undated (Box 1:17)
    - Manuscript (different versions),1970 (Box 1:18)
    - Notes (photocopies of notes originally written on folders),undated (Box 1:19)
    - Requests for Materials,undated, 1973 (Box 1:20)
    - Notes; early drafts of sections of book,undated (Box 1:21)
    - Copy of Declaration of Independence; pamphlets about Declaration of Independence,undated, 1956 (Box 1:22)
    - Lists of Signers; copies of signatures,undated, 1971-1976 (Box 1:23)
    - Booklets about signatures of presidents and signers,undated, 1935-1967 (Box 1:24)
    - Materials relating to sales and auctions of presidents' and signers' signatures,undated, 1961-1973 (Box 1:25)
    - Articles about bookplates of signers,undated, 1905-1970 (Box 1:26)
    - Articles about Revolutionary War,undated, 1973-1980 (Box 1:27)
    - Thomas Jefferson; Jefferson's interest in books,undated, 1751-1976 (Box 1:28)
    - Nathaniel and Benjamin Hurd,undated, 1979 (Box 1:29)
    - First American Law School,1969-1976 (Box 1:30)
    - Homony Club,undated, 1975-1979 (Box 1:31)
    - Information about books about English bookplates,undated (Box 1:32)
    - Bicentennial materials,undated, 1972-1975 (Box 1:33)
    - First American National Bank,1970-1971 (Box 1:34)
    - Colonial Williamsburg (pamphlets and guidebook),undated, 1937-1964 (Box 1:35)
    - Connecticut pamphlets (Lebanon, Norwich),undated, 1959 (Box 1:36)
    - George Washington and Mt. Vernon,undated, 1939-1970 (Box 1:37)
    - Making quill pens,1973-1975 (Box 1:38)
    - Benjamin Franklin chair; antique Windsor chairs,1967-1975 (Box 1:39)
    - Flags,undated, 1962-1971 (Box 1:40)
    - Signers' Correspondence
      - General Correspondence Relating to Signers,undated, 1953-1968 (Box 2:41)
      - Allen, Francis,undated, [1950?]-1976 (Box 2:42)
      - American Antiquarian Society,Sep 1946-Dec 1976 (Box 2:43)
      - Benjamin, Mary (Walter R. Benjamin Autographs),Jan 1954-Mar 1966 (Box 2:44)
      - Berryman, Florence Seville,Jan 1925-Jun 1967 (Box 2:45)
      - Colonial Williamsburg,Oct 1949-Jul 1974 (Box 2:46)
      - Ginsberg, Louis,Feb 1966-Jul 1971 (Box 2:47)
      - The Library Company of Philadelphia,Feb 1973-Mar 1973 (Box 2:48)
      - The Manuscript Society,1971 Sep 9-13 (Box 2:49)
      - Turner, Justin,undated, 1951-1975 (Box 2:50)
      - Wyatt, Leo,undated, 1975-1976 (Box 2:51)
      - Adams, John,undated (Box 2:52)
      - Anderson, Alexander,1961 Feb-Oct (Box 2:53)
      - Carroll, Charles,undated, 1955-1976 (Box 2:54)
      - Chase, Samuel,Oct 1955-Apr 1975 (Box 2:55)
      - Clymer, George,1971 Aug 21 (Box 2:56)
      - Gwinnett, Button,May 1967-May 1971 (Box 2:57)
      - Hooper, William,1979 Jun 13 (Box 2:58)
      - Lynch, Thomas,undated, 1966-1971 (Box 2:59)
      - Morris, Lewis,1974-Jan-Feb (Box 2:60)
      - Paca, William,undated, 1967 Jun-Aug (Box 2:61)
      - Read, George,1979 Jun 13 (Box 2:62)
      - Rush, Benjamin,1972-1975 (Box 2:63)
      - Wilson, James,undated, 1971-1972 (Box 2:64)
      - Wolcott, Oliver,1970-1975 (Box 2:65)
      - Correspondence Concerning the Trumball Painting of The Declaration of Independence,1966 Jul-Aug (Box 2:66)
      - Correspondence Concerning Thomas Jefferson's Desk and Inkwell Used for Declaration of Independence,Mar 1966-Nov 1975 (Box 2:67)
    - Signers' Biographical and Bookplate Information
      - Adams, John,undated (Box 2:68)
      - Anderson, Alexander,undated, 1870 (Box 2:69)
      - Carroll, Charles,undated, 1894-1982 (Box 2:70)
      - Chase, Samuel,undated, 1896-1971 (Box 2:71)
      - Clymer, George,undated, 1805 Jun (Box 2:72)
      - Gwinnett, Button,undated (Box 2:73)
      - Heyward, Thomas Jr.,undated (Box 2:74)
      - Hooper, William,undated (Box 2:75)
      - Hopkinson, Francis,undated (Box 2:76)
      - Lynch, Thomas,undated, 1895 Oct (Box 2:77)
      - McKean, Thomas,undated (Box 2:78)
      - Morris, Lewis,undated (Box 2:79)
      - Morris, Robert,undated (Box 2:80)
      - Paca, William,undated, 1968 (Box 2:81)
      - Read, George,undated (Box 2:82)
      - Rush, Benjamin,undated, 1975-1976 (Box 2:83)
      - Stockton, Richard,undated (Box 2:84)
      - Taylor, George,undated (Box 2:85)
      - Wilson, James,undated, 1940-1971 (Box 2:86)
      - Wolcott, Oliver,undated, 1797-1964 (Box 2:87)
      - Wythe, George,undated (Box 2:88)
- Business (Shop; Hilprand Press,undated, 1946-1979
  - Announcements; advertisements,undated, 1951-1966 (Box 2:89)
  - Hilprand Press Correspondence,1951 Feb- 1979 Jul (Box 2:90)
  - Mailing lists,1946-1952 (Box 2:91)
  - Order forms,1951-1966 (Box 2:92)
  - Printed matter,1970 (Box 2:93)
  - Bibliography of Medical Ex-Libris Literature by Samuel X. Radbill, M.D., 1951
    - Manuscript,1951 Jun 28 (Box 2:94)
    - Announcements,undated, 1951-1969 (Box 2:95)
    - Reviews,1951-1955 (Box 2:96)
  - Correspondence
    - General correspondence,1951 Mar- 1970 May (Box 2:97)
    - Anthoensen Press,1951- 1952 May (Box 2:98)
    - Mention of book in other publications,1951 Aug-1953 Mar (Box 2:99)
- General Correspondence,undated, 1944-1978
  - General,undated, 1944-1978 (Box 2:100)
  - Correspondence regarding research grants,1955-1973 (Box 2:101)
- Materials written about Clare,undated, 1934-1984
  - Clare's notes written about herself,undated (Box 2:102)
  - Articles,undated, 1934-1982 (Box 2:103)
  - "Who's Who" entries,1943-1978 (Box 2:104)
  - Obituary,1981 Oct 10 (Box 2:105)
  - Correspondence written to Clare's brother Laurence J. Ryan,1982-1984 (Box 2:106)
- Photographs and Negatives,undated, 1913-1985
  - Photos of Clare Talbot, her shop, and displays,1913-1985 (Box 2:107)
  - Photos of signers' bookplates and portraits,undated (Box 2:108)
  - Photos of Jefferson Inkwell,undated (Box 2:109)
  - Photos of Justin Turner and his library,undated, 1966 (Box 2:110)
  - Negatives of signers' bookplates and portraits,undated (Box 2:111)